<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a libell written by D. Cosens against the great Generall councell of Laterane under Pope Innocent the Third wherein the many and great errors of the said D. Cosens are manifested to the world / by Thomas Vane.</title>
            <author>Vane, Thomas, fl. 1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V81</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07985287</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07985287</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1217:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a libell written by D. Cosens against the great Generall councell of Laterane under Pope Innocent the Third wherein the many and great errors of the said D. Cosens are manifested to the world / by Thomas Vane.</title>
                  <author>Vane, Thomas, fl. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 97, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [101]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cosin, John, 1594-1672.</term>
               <term>Lateran Council --  (4th : 1215)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40746:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER TO A LIBELL, WRITTEN BY D. COSENS AGAINST THE GREAT Generall Councell of Laterane under Pope Innocent the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein the many and great errors of the ſaid D. Coſens, are manifeſted to the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS VANE Doctor in Diuinity of Cambridge.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Tim. 3.13.</hi>
               </bibl> But euill men and ſeducers shall waxe worſe and worſe, deceiuing, and being deceiued.</q>
            <p>Printed at PARIS Anno Dom. 1646. <hi>With Permiſsion &amp; Approbation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40746:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40746:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST NOBLE AND MOST ACCOMPLISHED Gentleman, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> KENELME DIGBY KNIGHT &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I doe not dedicate this, crauing your protection thereof againſt calumny, and cenſure; the greateſt Princes (I know) cannot doe it; yea their owne perſons are not cenſure-proofe againſt the meaneſt varlets. Nor hereby to engage you to any fauour or defence thereof, beyond the direction of your owne iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; your free minde (I know) disdaynes to ſtoope to ſuch a lure, and mine to caſt it out. Let the booke ſuffer its owne fate, for ſo it will; hee that finds fault with it, let him tell mee ſo? and if I cannot defend it, I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the error. Nor to take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:40746:3"/> to flatter you; you are aboue it: and impoſsible attempts vanish euen in the vndertaking. Nor yet to pay you your due prayſe, I am below it; and Fame her ſelfe diſchargeth that debt, borrowing the tongues of all men for her helpe: But to teſtifie the honour I beare you, for your tranſcendent worth in your ſelfe; and the gratitude, for your great fauours to mee. It wants proportion (I confeſſe) to either; which proceeds from my pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of materialls: but as ſmall pictures compar'd with greater tables, ſo this (being all I haue to offer) may preſent mee as liuely, though not ſo largely</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and obliged ſeruant, THO. VANE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40746:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER, Doctor Coſens (ſince his coming into theſe parts) hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers againſt the Catholique doctrine and beliefe; and hath shewed them, or deliuered the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in diſcourſe to diuers perſons, thereby to draw them, or keepe them from the Catholique Communion; who not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ability or leiſure to examine their truth, I beleeue, thought better of them than they deſerued. Theſe papers of his came afterwards into the hands of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Catholiques, and each one anſwered that which hee hapned on, or which was (if any was) more particularly addreſſed to him; which is the reaſon that hee hath more anſwerers than one, though to them all, any one was more than enough. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his papers, this against the fowrth Councell of Lateran came to my hands, to which I ſoone after returned a briefe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40746:4"/> and ſo the matter reſted; but hearing ſince that hee, and ſome that thinke well of him, haue triumphed in theſe his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, as though hee had gayned great victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; that I might vndeceiue them, for ſo much as I vndertooke, (if at least they will ſuffer it,) and to informe all others, that pleaſe to reade, I thought good à little to enlarge my former anſwer, and to print it with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Carres. And others there are, at leaſt one other, that I know, who if hee thought fit to print what hee hath written in anſwer to Doctor Coſens, could perhaps diſcouer more corruptions of his than we haue done. But heere are more than enough to warrant vs to ſay of him, as<note n="a" place="margin">1. kings 5.25.</note> Abigal ſaid of Nabal; for by his deeds he makes true the ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his name: and that they that rely on him, will bee like thoſe that leane on a broken reedy ſtaffe, which will run into their hands, and wound inſteed of ſupporting them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40746:4"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>D.C. OF THE GREAT GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell of Lateran vnder Innocentius the third; ſaid to bee <hi>Maximum &amp; celeberrimum Concilium, Anno Domini</hi> 1215.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AXIMVM, for the number of eight hundred Priors and Abbots (who had no voyces in Councells but by priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from the Pope) was as great againe as the number of the Bishops.</hi> Celeberrimum, <hi>for it was euery where famous for this one thing of ſpeciall note in it, that ſo many men met together to no purpoſe; met, but did nothing. Therfore of this ſo Great and ſo famous a Councell, theſe be the words of Platina, (who was the Popes owne Secretary,) in vita Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40746:5"/> III.</hi> Venere multa tum quidem in conſultationem, nec decerni tamen quicquam apertè potuit, quòd &amp; Piſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni &amp; Genuenſes maritimo, &amp; Ciſalpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni terreſtri bello interſe certarent. Eò itaque proficiſcens tollendae diſcordiae cauſa Pontifex, Peruſii moritur. <hi>And to the ſame purpoſe are the words of Matth. Paris</hi> (in Hiſtoria minori) <hi>who liued in the ſame time when this Councell was called together.</hi> Concilium illud Generale, quod more papali, grandia prima fronte prae ſe tulit, in riſum &amp; ſcomma deſiit, quo Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopos, Epiſcopos, Abbates, Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Archidiaconos, omneſque ad id Concilium accedentes ludificatus eſt. <hi>(For after the Pope was gone to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the tumults betweene the Genuenſes and them of Piſa, there was nothing done)</hi> Et cum nihil geri in tanto negotio cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerent, redeundi ad ſua cupidi, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam ſigillatim petierunt. Quibus Papa non conceſſit, antequam ſibi grandem pecuniam promiſiſſent, quam a mercatoribus Romanis prius accipere mutuò, Papaeque ſoluere coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40746:5"/> ſunt, antequam diſcedere Roma potuiſſent. Papa iam accepta pecunia, quaeſtuoſum Concilium diſſoluit gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, totuſque Clerus abiit triſtis.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>It was called, <hi>Maximum,</hi> you ſay, for the number of eight hundred Priors and Abbots, (who had no voyce in Councell but by priuiledge from the Pope) was as great againe as the number of the Bishops. Tis true that it was iuſtly called <hi>maximum</hi> partly for this reaſon, though not for this only, for the number of voyces, not only of Bishops who haue their ſuffrages by common right, but euen of Abbots and Priors, who haue theirs by the Popes grant, doth main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribute to the greatneſſe of a Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell. Yet ſuppoſe the greatneſſe of this Councell be to be meaſured by the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Bishops only, how many can there be named greater? but very few in the world; and therfore it may well be called, <hi>Maximum.</hi> And <hi>Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berrimum</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40746:6"/> alſo; not, that ſo many met together, but did nothing, (as you ſay;) but becauſe there were preſent the Pope in perſon, two Patriarchs in perſon, and the other two by their Legats, the Greeke and Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours by their Legats, the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours of the kings of France, Spaine, England, Hieruſalem and Cyprus, with others; as I shall proue anon. But if to be famous for doing nothing, and for being to no purpoſe deſerue the title of <hi>Celeberrimum,</hi> theſe goodly obiections, when they are well knowne, will iuſtly beare that title on their brow.</p>
                  <p>You further tell vs, that Platina (whoſe words you cite) was the Popes owne Secretary: and you doe it either to no purpoſe, or elſe to inſinuate, that therfore hee was more knowing in the truth of the ſtory, or the more faithfull hiſtorian, or both. For the former, it had indeed beene likely, if hee had beene Secretary to the Pope, vnder whom this Councell aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as any one would thinke you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40746:6"/> meant, when you added this note in ſuch a weighty parentheſis. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that Platina was borne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares after the celebration of this Councell, and died in the yeare 1481. which was aboue 260. yeares after this Councell; as ſaith Trithemius de ſcriptorib. Eccleſ. as hee is cited in the workes of Platina, the page before the Epiſtle. This therfore is but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfull inſinuation of yours. Or if you did not ſay this with intent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue others, but were your ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; ſurely your care to informe your ſelfe well before you write, is very ſmall. Beſides if it were true, that hee had beene the Popes <hi>owne</hi> Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, as for greater <hi>emphaſis</hi> you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, yet his authority cannot counterpoyſe the authority of all that are of a contrary mind, (to that you thinke Platina was of,) whom I shall by and by produce. And laſtly Platina doth not affirme to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of this Councell, that which you erroneously imagine hee doth, as I shall preſently shew. As for his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40746:7"/> faithfullneſſe, I doe not thinke you will make his being the Popes owne Secretary an argument therof; men of your coate are not ſuch honourers of the Pope.</p>
                  <p>Now for the words themſelues of Platina, you misvnderſtand them; for you apply thoſe words, <hi>nec decerni ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quicquam aperte potuit,</hi> generally, to the whole buſineſſe of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, whereas the intent of them, at the moſt, is but particular concerning the Holy Land, as the fore-going words doe shew, which are theſe: <hi>At Pontifex vbi videret Saracenorum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam in Aſia concreſcere, apud Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranum, maximum Concilium celebrat. Venere multa tum quidem in conſultatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, nec decerni tamen quicquam apertè potuit, quod &amp; Piſani &amp; Genuenſes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritimo, &amp; Ciſalpini terreſtri bello interſe certabant.</hi> Theſe words then, <hi>nec decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni tamen quicquam apertè potuit,</hi> are at the moſt to bee referred to the bui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of the Holy Land, of ſending ayde thither, and making reſiſtance againſt the Turkes in Aſia, and to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40746:7"/> nothing elſe. And the reaſon why nothing could bee decreed in that matter, was the warres hee mentions, which could not bee a hindrance from their making of other Canons in that Councell.</p>
                  <p>And as it is apparent enough, that this at moſt, was the meaning of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina, to wit, that nothing was decreed concerning the Holy warre; and that therfore this place makes nothing to your purpoſe, who hereby would make voyde all the Canons of this Councell; ſoe it is alſo apparent that Platina (if ſoe much was his meaning) was deceiued euen in that; and that there was ſomething decreed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſending of aſſiſtance to the Holy Land, as appeareth by the decree of the Expedition, which is at the end of the Canons, whoſe truth I shall further proue by and by. Yea, and that Platina did not ſoe much as deny the decree of the Expedition, in his words, <hi>nec decerni quicquam aperté potuit,</hi> is very probable; for then hee would rather haue ſaid, <hi>nec decerni
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40746:8"/> quicquam potuit,</hi> abſolutely; but his qualification of it by the word <hi>apertè,</hi> ſeemes to grant that ſomething was done, though not <hi>apertè.</hi> And that ſomething was decreed, is manifeſt by that which I shall ſay hereafter; what then hee meanes by theſe words, <hi>nec apertè,</hi> in that which was decreed, is not manifeſt. Perhaps by Decree, hee meanes the execution of the Decree, in actuall warring againſt the Turkes, wherein there was nothing openly done, whatſoeuer might bee ſecretly done tending to their preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. If this bee his meaning, (as no other can bee with truth in the thing) then, though his words bee obſcure, and improper to ſignifie thus much, yet his meaning is true, but nothing to your purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>But Nauclerus doth open this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, and makes it cleere againſt you; for hee ſpeaking of the ſame bui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and vſing the ſame words with Platina, in the reſt, inſteed of Platina's <hi>apertè,</hi> hee ſaith <hi>aptè;</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Vol.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.914.</note> 
                     <hi>nec de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerni tamen quicquam aptè potuit, quod &amp; Piſani &amp; Genuenſes &amp;c.</hi> There could
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40746:8"/> nothing bee fitly, conueniently, and to the purpoſe decreed in regard of the tyme becauſe of the warres in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope. And immediatly after hee ſaith, (to confute that which you ſay, that there was nothing done heere) <hi>Editae tamen nonnullae conſtitutiones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feruntur,</hi> but there are diuers conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions declared to bee made.</p>
                  <p>As for Matthew Paris his <hi>Hiſtoriae minor,</hi> I cannot meet with it, and in the volume of his whole workes both <hi>maior</hi> and <hi>minor,</hi> ſet forth lately by D. Wats of London: I can finde no ſuch words as you cite. And if you had beene willing that your quotation should haue beene examined, you would haue giuen a man a neerer ayme than a whole hiſtory, whether <hi>maior</hi> or <hi>minor,</hi> to finde it in, eſpecially in a quotation ſo important to your mayne deſigne; vnleſſe you meant to giue a man more trouble than is faire in one that writes a controuerſie. The like you haue alſo done in ſome of your following authorities. But if theſe words, <hi>Et cum nihil geri in tanto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40746:9"/> negotio cernerent,</hi> which are all that concerne your purpoſe, bee to bee found in him, hee ſpeakes of the ſame expedition of the Holy Land, and of the execution therof, not of the Decree it ſelfe, as the word <hi>geri</hi> will aſwell beare in its ſignification: and if hee mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t otherwiſe hee had no good intelligence in the buiſineſſe, (as I shall preſently proue;) for though hee liued in the ſame time of this Councell, yet hee liued in a farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place. And his words, <hi>in ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> doe ſurely poynt at ſome one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular matter, which though it haue beene the occaſion of calling many Councells, yet when the Prelats were met, they diſcuſſed and decreed many other things for the good of the Church. Soe that though it bee true that nothing was executed in the great buſineſſe of the Holy warres, by reaso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the warres in chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, yet it is farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prouing that which you ſoe boldly affirme, that neither the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the expedition for the Holy Land, nor any one Canon was made in this Councell. <hi>They met</hi> (ſay you)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40746:9"/> 
                     <hi>but did nothing;</hi> nor haue you (I am ſure) done any thing againſt them. And that you may further ſee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of this your Author, in matters concerning the perſon of this Pope, (which is the purport of all the other words by you alleadged out of him,) reade Baronius in his laſt tome, anno 1197. who telleth vs, that this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Paris ſeemeth to haue writ his hiſtory of purpoſe to take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſclander the Popes; and then reciting a ſtory, concludeth thus. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti Lector Parts ingenium, animique male compoſiti malam ſententiam, res fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, verbaque formare indigna Romano Pontifice, &amp; ab hoc vno tam patenti men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacio caetera diſcas, &amp; caueas vide aſque qua tunc ſit homo fide dignus, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> totus ſit in carpendis Rom. Eccleſ. Pontificibus.</hi> And therfore his accuſation of the Pope for exacting a great ſumme of mony of the Councell, firſt as it is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to your buiſineſſe, (for his couetounſeſſe could not nullifie the Canons of the Councell) ſo alſo is it moſt vnlikely to be true, becauſe Paris
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40746:10"/> is recorded for a ſlanderer, and Pope Innocent III. for a worthy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent man.<note n="d" place="margin">Naucle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus vol. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>876.</hi>
                     </note> Nauclerus calleth him, <hi>vir doctrina &amp; moribus inſignis.</hi> And Platina, in his life, ſaith, <hi>conſtat cum in quouis genere vitae probatiſsimum fuiſſe, dignumque qui inter Sanctos Pontifices cenſeatur.</hi> And againe in the next words to thoſe you cite, <hi>cuius vita adeo probata fuit, vt poſt eius mortem, nihil eorum quae in vita egerit, laudanerit, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probaueritque, immutatum eſt.</hi> The ſame alſo ſaith Nauclerus; and adds, <hi>quin &amp; religionis apprimè ſtudioſus.</hi> But you are glad to cite any thing to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement of à Pope, though there be no colour of truth for it.</p>
                  <p>Now that nothing at all was done in this Councell, which is the mayne matter you driue at,<note n="e" place="margin">Vol. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>915.</hi>
                     </note> &amp; for which you haue misinterpreted the meaning of Platina and Paris, is very vntrue. Which I proue, firſt by the authority of Gregory IX. who liued in the time of this Councell, and was created Pope but about eleuen yeares after, and commanded the Decrees should
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40746:10"/> be put in the body of the Canon law, wherein hee vſed the ſeruice of Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus, of whom Platina thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <note n="e" place="margin">In vita Greg. IX. fine.</note> 
                     <hi>Raymundum autem Barchino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſem, quo adiutore in compilando libro Decretalium, Gregorius vſus eſt, ita qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam tàm laudant,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">So ſay the Annal Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ poſt Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron tom <hi>13.</hi> p. <hi>439</hi> XV.</note> 
                     <hi>vt maiori commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione laudari nemo poſsit.</hi> And Binius in the life of the ſayd Gregory IX ſaith that this Raymundus was Canonized by Clement VIII.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">S. Thom. <hi>4.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>17.</hi> q <hi>3.</hi> art. <hi>1</hi> ad tertiam.</note> I proue it by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the greateſt Diuines of that age, S. Thomas, and S. Bonauenture, who ſpeaking of the precept of yearly confeſſion,<note place="margin">S Bonau. <hi>4.</hi> ſent diſt. <hi>17</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> arg. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> ſay that the Church did inſtitute it, and the Fathers command it in this Councell.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, by the teſtimony of the Councell of Trent, which ſpeaking of the ſame Decree, calls it,<note place="margin">Conc. Tria ſeſſ. <hi>14</hi> can <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the great Lateran Councell.</hi> And that the Acts of this Councell were alwayes extant, and are not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait, appeares, in that they now are, and haue beene in the body of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non law, euer ſince the time of Greg,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40746:11"/> IX. who commanded them to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted; and<note n="f" place="margin">Annal. Eccleſ. poſt Baron. tom. <hi>13.</hi> anno <hi>1234.</hi> XV.</note> 
                     <hi>anno 1234.</hi> which were but nineteene yeares after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, approued the collection. Neither could any man haue meanes to know the truth of the Canons better than hee, the Councell hauing beene held not long before, by his vncle, in that citty, where hee being Pope could command the ſight of all the monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and many were ſtill aliue who had beene preſent in the Councell ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated but nineteene yeares before the publishing of theſe Canons, &amp; knew therfore what was done in it, better than thoſe who were further remoued, either in time as Platina was, or in place as was Matthew Paris, if they had (as you ſuppoſe) ſaid any thing againſt it. Nor was it likely that Pope Gregory either would or could haue obtruded them before the eyes of ſuch great Prelats and Princes, for decrees made in Councell, had they not beene ſo indeed. Nor would the Church (the things there determined ſoe much concerning her) nor they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40746:11"/> who did ſoe much emulate her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, haue beene ſilent, had ſuch a thing beene attempted.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly I proue that there were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons made in this Councell, yea and that thoſe Canons were receiued in England, (a thing which you deny towards the end of your diſcourſe) by a<note n="f" place="margin">Matth. Paris. hiſt. ma. anno <hi>1222.</hi>
                     </note> generall Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell (ſo it is ſtiled) of England, held at Oxford, by Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen Archbishop of Canterbury, in the yeare 1222. which was but ſeuen yeares after this of Lateran, and about 12. yeares before the Canons therof were put into the Decretalls by Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory IX. where towards the end it is ſaid,<note n="g" place="margin">Binij Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. tom. <hi>7.</hi> part. <hi>2.2.</hi> fol. <hi>833.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Vt autem omnia fine bono conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantur, Lateranenſe Concilium ſub ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae recordationis Papa Innocentio cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratum, in praeſtatione decimarum in aliis capitulis praecipimus obſeruari.</hi> But this is not all you haue to ſay againſt this Councell;</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>There be many things beſides, which may make vs iuſtly to ſuſpect the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this pretended great Councell. For
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40746:12"/> firſt, before Cochlaeus put it forth, it was neuer extant; and it was but lately neither that hee put it forth, in the yeare 1538. Three yeares before, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Merlin put forth the Councells; there was no ſuch Councell, that hee met withall, to ſet out; it is not in his edition. But Cochlaeus (a man not ſo well to be truſted, &amp; who feigned many things in writing Luthers life) tells vs, that hee had the Decrees of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell out of an antient booke; but where hee got that booke, or who firſt compiled it, or of what authority it was, hee tells vs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all. It is moſt likely, that antient booke was no other but the booke of the Popes Decretalls, where thoſe things that are ſaid by him to be decreed in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, are heere and there ſcattered in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places. Thoſe ſcatterings (I belieue) did Cochlaeus, or ſome other, collect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and made vp one body of them in manner and forme of a Councell. But ſo ill-fauored a forme hath hee giuen it, that often it betrayeth it ſelfe not to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine, and taken out of any authenticke coppy.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40746:12"/>
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>You further ſay, that there are many things beſides, which may make you iuſtly ſuſpect the authority of this <hi>pretended</hi> great Councell, as you are pleaſed to call it. I eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue that there are many things that make you not only to ſuſpect, but flatly to reiect the authority of this and many other Generall Councells, but none iuſtly. But it is not the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this Generall Councell, (which is the ſame in all,) but the verity of the Canons and Decrees therof (you would haue ſayd) and the authority of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that affirme thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, that you with ſo much ſagacity ſuſpect. And if you thinke the Councell and the Canons thereof but pretended, which are acknowledged true by the voyce of all the Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of the world, what shall make them to be accounted reall? or shall the voyce, of one pretended Deane di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish their reality? And if you thinke this Councell but pretendedly Great, which conſiſted of the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40746:13"/> of the greateſt perſons both Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall and ſecular, that euer met together in the world, I muſt needs thinke that the common ſence and vnderſtanding of a man, is in you but pretended. Doth not Platina <hi>the Popes owne Secretary,</hi> cloſe by the words cited by you, ſay, <hi>Pontifex apud Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranum, maximum Concilium celebrat?</hi> And doth not your owne Mathew Paris, in the words by you cited, ſay <hi>Concilium illud Generale?</hi> beſides many more and better witneſſes. And can you after all this, call it ſoe ſcornefully a pretended Great Councell? yea no Generall Councell, no Councell at all? as you doe in the latter end of your pamphlet. Surely you are Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liath that defie the whole hoſte of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raël, yet euery one, though as little as Dauid, is able to cut of your head, with your owne ſword.</p>
                  <p>Now the grounds of your ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherby you would diſmount the Canons of this great Councell, are ſo feeble, that they shew you are no skilfull enginier. Wherof one is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40746:13"/> Merlin hath it not in his edition, hee could not meet with it, to ſet it forth. But this is a poore argument; for firſt wee know that there were many other Councells which Merlin could not meet with, which haue ſince beene put forth, and Proteſtants I thinke will not deny, that there were ſuch, as the ſecond of Nice, fower of Lateran, two of Lions, one of Vienne, and one of Florence; and this of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was celebrated later than any that hee ſets downe, and was the laſt Generall one that was held before his publishing of his booke, about fower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares before it. And yet it ſeemes that hee could not meet with the Records of this Councell, or elſe hee did purpoſely omit it, which is not likely, how much more eaſy then was it for him to miſſe this of Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, which was held about 300. yeares before. Beſides, it is manifeſt that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the world at that time, nor hee himſelfe did belieue, that hee had ſet forth all the Councells; as appeares by the king of France his Priuiledge at the beginning of his worke, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40746:14"/> his owne words at the end of his Epiſtle before the ſecond volume. The words of the kings Priuiledge are theſe, <hi>Concilia quae in Eccleſia à tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Apoſtolorum vſque ad conceſſum Baſilienſem celebrata potuerunt coacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uari,</hi> by which it appeares that as they were all that they could then get, ſo they were not abſolutely and certainly all that were. The words of Merlin himſelfe are theſe. <hi>Nam ſi authentica, integra, ſolida, &amp; à me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis expertia fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaria, vnde haec fideliter excerp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt, apprime caſtigata ſunt, pura, vera, &amp; ſincera quae profero, ſuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Archetyporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quidem germanam conditionem prae ſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia, quae ſi grato animo tuleris, prope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diem (confide) ampliora noſtris te ſudori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aſſecuturum:</hi> by which it likewiſe appeares that hee did belieue that there were diuers others which hee had not ſet downe. Now for you to inferre that becauſe hee could not meet with this Councell of Lateran, therfore there was none ſuch, is a very vniuſt conſequence, and is as ſtrong againſt the eight other aboue named, as againſt this.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40746:14"/>
                  <p>Another ground of your shrewd ſuſpition is, becauſe Cochlaeus firſt put it forth, and becauſe hee put it forth but lately; ſoe that you obiect both againſt the perſon, and againſt the time. For the perſon of Cochlaeus, you ſay, hee was not a man ſo well to bee truſted; and to make that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, you ſay, that hee feigned ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things in writing Luthers life. Againſt the time of Cochlaeus his edition you obiect, becauſe it was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth, to wit, in the yeare 1538. three yeares after Merlin ſet forth his edition of the Councells. I will firſt conſider the truth of what you ſay, and then the force therof. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Cochlaeus his edition of this or any other Councell, I can find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that Bellarmine in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies reckons him amongſt ſuch as haue writ of the Councells, yet hee doth not reckon it amongſt the cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of his workes, in his booke de Script. Eccleſ. nor can I find is heere in Paris. Yet taking what you ſay in this for granted, I doe not find that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40746:15"/> hee was a man leſſe to be truſted than Merlin, or any other; for Bell: calleth him, <hi>Vir doctiſsimus, &amp; fidei Catholicae propugnator eximius;</hi> and therfore you who traduce a man without any proofe are much leſſe to be truſted than he: yea than any man I know, for your many falſifications, proued both in this and your other writings. As for your ſaying that <hi>hee faigned many things in writing Luthers life,</hi> that is but a new slander which as you doe not offer to proue, ſo it is impoſſible you should; for how can you know the heart of another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from whence his faigning muſt proceed? Hee may indeed write that which is falſe, but that hee did ſo by his owne fiction, and not by others misinformation, you cannot be aſſured, vnleſſe hee himſelfe had confeſſed it, which you doe not proue that hee hath. Nor doe you proue ſo much as that hee hath written any thing falſe of Luther.</p>
                  <p>You alſo ſuſpect Cochlaeus his edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Councells in regard of the time, becauſe hee ſet it forth lately.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40746:15"/> And what I pray, is lately? you ſay, the yeare 1538. which is a hundred and eight yeares agoe. Indeed in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the Apoſtles times it is but lately, but in compariſon of the inuention of printing, which was but about two hundred yeares agoe, and according to the ordinary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſchollers in editions of bookes, I belieue none will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count a booke ſet forth a hundred and eight yeares agoe, a thing lately ſet forth. Much leſſe haue you reaſon to accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it ſo, ſeing you doe not account Merlins ſo, which yet (as you ſay) was ſet out but three yeares before. It is a paradox to ſay, Merlin an antient writer in the yeare 1535. Cochlaeus a late writer in the yeare 1538. Can three yeares odds in a hundred and eleuen make one to be called late, and therfore to be (as you ſay) ſuſpected, and not the other? Surely if this your argument of lateneſſe be good againſt one, it is ſo againſt both; wherby you may, according to your prudence, ſuſpect all the Councells ſet forth by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40746:16"/> Merlin. But I will giue your ſuſpition yet more ſcope; for Merlin published the Councells in the yeare 1524. as appeares by the laſt words of the whole worke; ſo that Cochlaeus his edition was full fourteene yeares after Merlins, according to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Cochlaeus. And now to turne the poynt of your argument vpon your ſelfe, this laterneſſe of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chlaeus is ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being a ground of ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it is (by iuſt ſo much) a ſtronger confirmation of the truth and exactneſſe of his worke. It was but by accident that the Councells were printed at any time; they might haue beene let alone till this preſent yeare, or not printed at all, would that haue made you ſuſpect the truth of them all? it would then haue made the world ſuſpect you for à very weake man, or rather haue put you below all ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But it ſo falling out that the Councells were printed at ſeuerall times, by the care of ſeuerall men, the later they were printed, the more mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes had the publisher to make further
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40746:16"/> ſearch, and to enforme himſelfe out of the Manuſcripts more fully; as wee find, that in all editions of bookes, the lateſt (if the publisher apply due dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence) are moſt full, moſt pure, and moſt correct. I hope you will not ſay that the late edition of S. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Henry Sauill, is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more ſuſpitious. So that heere is neither truth in the grounds of your ſuſpition, nor reaſon that this laſt should be any ground, though it were true.</p>
                  <p>You ſay moreouer, that Cochlaeus ſayes, that hee had the Decrees of this Councell out of an antient booke, but where hee got that booke, or who firſt compiled it, or of what authority it was, hee tells vs nothing at all. And you adde your coniecture, as weake as your former ſuſpition, that it is moſt likely, that that booke was the Popes Decretalls, where the ſuppoſed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of This Councell are ſcattered in ſeuerall places. Concerning Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus I can ſay nothing, ſeeing I cannot meet (as I ſaid before) with this his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40746:17"/> worke that you cite, but I will fauour you ſo farre as to ſuppoſe you ſay true, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the purpoſe of it, which indeed is none at all. But for that hee had it out of an ancient booke is much to his purpoſe, which booke (I will be bold to coniecture, ſeeing you are ſo for your liking) was the very Originall of the Councell it ſelfe; and where hee got it, is impertinent for you to demand. And for this my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture I will giue you good ground, this, that in Crabs edition of the Councells I finde an Epiſtle to the Reader before the beginning of this Councell, the title wherof is this; <hi>Bartholomeus Laurens Nouimagenſis, Lectori;</hi> the beginning of the Epiſtle this. <hi>Haec ſunt quae ex Archetypo illo cuius ſupra mentio fit, lectu adeo difficili, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo labore deſcripſimus; quae ſi cui grata &amp; vtilia fuerint, primum gratias agat Deo, qui horum qualecunque exemplar hucuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſeruauit; deinde F. Petro Crab, qui hoc ipſum vt inter Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cilia ederetur, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauit.</hi> And this perhaps is the preface which you mention hereafter and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40746:17"/> to Cochlaeus, for other I finde not. But whoſe ſoeuer it was, it proues thus much, that this Councell (which was firſt published (that I can find) by Peter Crab) was taken out of the Original Record, than which there can be no better authority; and ſo hee ſaith againe in the body of his Epiſtle, <hi>certè in editione hac ſedulo curatum eſt, ne quicquam ei ab Archetypo alienum ingeri poſſet.</hi> And in this edition is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the expeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the others, which in particular you hereafter ſeeke to nullifie, wherby thoſe obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are beforehand anſwered; yet I will ſay more when I come to them. But ſuppoſe the Decrees of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell had beene taken out of the Popes Decretalls (the originall being loſt, as were the Canons of the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Nice, which makes ſo much vncertainty about the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) into which they were inſerted (as I shewed before) by Gregory the ninth, but a few yeares after they were made; in ſeuerall places, according to the ſeuerall titles to which they were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40746:18"/> to be referred (which you diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call ſcattering) what impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this vnto their credit? The Popes Decretalls are a teſtimony of no ſmall reputation amongſt all learned Chriſtians. And why I pray ſcatterings? the Decretalls are not a collection of the Councells, that ſo you should expect euery Canon in his order, but à digeſtion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of all the Councells that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to one matter, vnder one head; like the collection of the Statutes of England by Raſtall and others; (out of which if one would vndertake to extract all the lawes made in Queene Elizabeths raigne, hee muſt looke perhaps in a hundred ſeuerall places) which yet I thinke you will not call ſcattering, but methodicall digeſtion. But theſe are the reproaches throwne vpon the chiefe ſpirituall father of the Chriſtian world, by thoſe whom God hath (like Symeon and Leui) for the cruell ſchiſme they haue made in the Church, <hi>diuided in Iaacob and ſcattered in Iſrael.</hi> But from whence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40746:18"/> ſoeuer the firſt publisher of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell tooke the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thereof, certaine it is that they were acknowledged, and aſcribed to this Councell, by a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony aboue all exception, namely, of the whole clergy of England in a Councell at Oxford, as I haue shewed before, &amp; that, 12. yeares before the booke of the Decretalls was compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. So that from the Decretalls is not the firſt view that wee haue of the Canons of this Councell.</p>
                  <p>You againe repeat, and ſay, Thoſe <hi>ſcatterings</hi> (you belieue) Cochlaeus or ſome other did collect together, and made vp one body of them in manner and forme of a Councell. But ſo ill fauoured a forme hee hath giuen it, that it often betrayeth it ſelfe not to be genuine, and taken out of any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique coppie. Euen now you ſayd (without doubt) that it was Cochlaeus that ſet forth this Councell, now, it was hee or ſome other; and this I muſt needs grant is very true; for if it be ſet forth, certainly it was either by one or another. And if it were not Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40746:19"/> then haue you loſt much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in ſeeking to poyſon his credit herein. And if it were ſome other, then is your decrying this Councell by reaſon of this edition of Cochlaeus, of no force, for then I affirme, that this <hi>ſome other,</hi> was a man of the greateſt credit of all other, and ſo the caſe is cleere againſt you, out of your owne words, and you ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing heere to impeach the credit of this other; which I wonder at, for you may aſwell ſpeake againſt you know not whom, as ſay you know not what, as you doe in all this diſcourſe. You tooke it ill of Cochlaeus that hee did not tell you where hee had that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient booke; and haue not wee much more reaſon to take it ill of you, that will not tell vs who it was that firſt put forth this Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell you ſo much finde fault with, nor giue vs any ayme to finde out this editio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you meane (writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by you know not whom) from any other? but although you heere fayle vs, yet you thinke you come home to vs in that which followes;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40746:19"/> and although you know not who firſt put forth this Councell, and that wee know that both firſt and laſt haue done it in the ſame manner; yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out relation to the publisher, the very forme of this Councell, you ſay is ſo ill fauoured, that it often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayeth it ſelfe not to be genuine, and taken out of any authentique coppy. Which deepe charge of yours againſt this Councell will recoyle vpon your ſelfe, and by the ill fauoured forme therof, betray it ſelfe not to be ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly, nor taken out of any authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que coppy, either of reaſon or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>For ſecondly, who will belieue? who can perſuade himſelfe, that this Councell of Lateran should cite the Councell of Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran in the Decrees and Canons which were there compiled? that is, that it should cite it ſelfe, as à Councell not now ſitting, but paſſed and held a long time (or ſome time at leaſt) before it? The stile of other Councells vſeth to be, <hi>Haec ſancta Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus decernit,</hi> or <hi>placuit huic Sanctae
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40746:20"/> Synodo,</hi> as a ſeſsion now in being, when they make their Decree. But this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Lateran ſpeakes of it ſelfe, as of ſome other Lateran Councell, then was at that time ſitting, <hi>Fuit, &amp; noſcitur fuiſſe,</hi> as of ſome decrees made before, ſix ſeuerall times together; once in the 11. chapt. twice in the <hi>29.</hi> three times more in the 33. <hi>46</hi> and <hi>61.</hi> Chapters. <hi>In Latera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cilio pia fuit inſtitutione pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſum. De multa prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia fuit in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cilio prohibitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Deuolua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur collatio ſecundum ſtatutum La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teranenſis Concilii. Et in Lateranenſi Concilio noſcitur fuiſſe prohibitum.</hi> Will any man thinke theſe be the words of the Councell of Lateran it ſelfe?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>Will any man thinke theſe be the words of a man that conſiders what hee ſayes? who will belieue, who can perſuade himſelfe, that a pillar of his ſect, should frame an accuſation againſt a Councell, which (to phraſe it moſt gently,) is (I belieue) the greateſt ouerſight that euer was yet committed in this kinde? You ſay that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40746:20"/> this Councell while it was ſitting, doeth cite it ſelfe, as a Councell that had ſitten ſome while before; and to proue it you alleadge ſix places, wherein there is mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Lateran; and you moſt weakly imagine, that the Councell of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran there ſpoken of, is this Councell of Lateran that ſpeaketh. Know then (and a great shame it is that you should be guilty of ſuch an ignorance, as not to know it before you framed this terrible obiection) that there were foure Councells of Lateran, (according to the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued opinion concerning the place) of which three were before this; and the Councell of Lateran cited in this, was that which was celebrated next before this, vnder Pope Alexander the third, in the yeare 1180, wherein all thoſe places you (more punctually than any other) doe alleadge, are to be found. And is it poſſible that you (who talke ſometimes, as if you had beene Secretary to all the Councells) could be ſo ignorant, as neuer to haue
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40746:21"/> read or heard of any Councell of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but this, ſo that finding in this the Councell of Lateran cited, you should thinke this Councell cited it ſelfe? for if you had but read this Councell in Binius, you should haue found all theſe places by you cited, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to their particular chapters, in the former Councell of Lateran, vnder Alexander the third. Or if any man had forged this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell (as you iniuriouſly to vs imagine) could you thinke him ſo ſilly a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, as to conceiue ſuch a groſſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity as this, should ſteale away vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſerued? And if hee did not belieue hee should alwayes eſcape vndiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, (as to his eternall vnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by your ſeuerer inquiſition, hee hath not,) could you thinke him ſo foolish as to doe a thing in it ſelfe moſt abſurd and impertinent, which had no end in it, (for it was all one whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Councell cited the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Lateran or no,) and which could arriue at no other end, but the ruine of that which was his maine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40746:21"/> deſigne, namely, the begetting of the worlds beliefe to this his edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Councell; to which he muſt needs foreſee, that this would be the vndoubted ouerthrow?</p>
                  <p>But howeuer, you make bold to ſlight and traduce ſome particular Catholiques, though moſt learned and vertuous, yet (to vſe a frequent word of your owne, but much more ſeaſonably) <hi>I wonder how you dare,</hi> ſo eaſily to condemne all Catholiques in generall; as to ſuppoſe that all the Popes, Catholique Bishops, Diuines, Canoniſts, and other learned men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable of the Catholique Church, yea thoſe whoſe intereſt is mightily concerned in this Councell, euen all temporall Princes, whoſe Lay-depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants are not few in number, nor faint in courage, nor all defectiue in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but ſome of them very eminent therein, were all ſo blind to this grand abſurdity as not to ſee it, if they were Clergy, not one amongſt ſo many millions not to haue ſo much feare of the God of heauen nor honeſty
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40746:22"/> as to diſcouer it; if they were of the Laity, not to haue ſo much regard to the God of this world, proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and to humane prudence, as to publish this prodigious forgery; but to ſuffer theſe Canons to be blanched ouer with the title of a great Generall Councell, and by that meanes cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant through the world, vntill you with much induſtry and art, come and diſcouer this long hidden ſecret, and myſtery of iniquity, to Catholiques eternall shame (as you ſurely thinke) and your owne eternall honour.</p>
                  <p>But now you may ſee, that when men with pride and obſtinacy fight againſt the truth, they fall into that pit of shame and folly, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for others. Yea you goe on with more courage than foreſight, thus;</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>Therfore thirdly, Cochlaeus is faine to excuſe the matter by a coniecture, (in his preface to this Councell ſet forth by Crab) that theſe decrees were collected and brought into this forme, wherein hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them, by Pope Innocentius himſelfe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40746:22"/> ſome while after the Councell was done. He cites three chap. of the Councell to that purpoſe, (three of thoſe ſix that are named afore) and ſayes, the Reader will eaſily deprehend aſmuch. But what reader will like it well, that the decrees of a Councell should be written ſome while after the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell is ended? It was alwayes the vſe of Councells to write their owne decrees, and to ſigne them too, before they went away. And Innocent the Pope was not ſo weake a Scribe, as to make the Synode it ſelfe ſpeake after ſuch a manner, <hi>In Laterane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi Concilio noſcitur fuiſſe prohibitum; or, fiat hoc, ſecundum quod prouiſum eſt in Lateranenſi Concilio &amp;c.</hi> which certainly is not the ſtile of the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell concerning it ſelfe; Innocent the third knew well enough what belonged to it.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>Firſt you made Cochlaeus guilty of a fowle fault, and now you bring him in making an excuſe, and both falſely. Firſt, I can finde no ſuch coniecture as you ſpeake of, and ſecondly if it were to be found, it is no excuſe. You ſay
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40746:23"/> it is to be found in his preface to this Councell ſet forth by Crab; but wee may ſooner gather the Sibylls leaues than finde it, for there is no ſuch thing. There is indeed an epiſtle of Bartholomaeus Laurens, which I haue mentioned before, &amp; by which you were confuted, it being thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that that edition was taken out of the originall, for which there needs no excuſe. Beſides, it is a thing in it ſelfe improbable, that Cochlaeus who (as you ſay) wrote this Councell himſelfe, should afterwards write a preface to another mans edition of the ſame Councell. But ſuppoſe this coniecture you mention (to wit, <hi>that theſe decrees were collected and brought into this forme he preſents them, by Pope Innocent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſome while after the Councell was done</hi>) be ſome where to be found; what excuſe is this I pray, or what doth it excuſe? If the coniecture be true, it confimes the whole cauſe againſt you: namely, that all theſe decrees were made in the Councell; if it be falſe, it is nothing. But you draw co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequences
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40746:23"/> from hence which are certainly moſt pittifull and inconſequent, with which while you thinke to ſtrengthen your cauſe, you doe weaken the credit of your owne vnderſtanding.</p>
                  <p>You ſay, what reader will like it well; that the decrees of a Councell should be written ſome while after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell is ended? And I ſay, what reader (but your captious ſelfe) will diſlike it? Indeed if the decrees of the Councell had beene written ſome while before the Councell began, you might iuſtly haue asked, who would haue liked it; but to aske who will like, that they should be written afterwards, is moſt ridiculous. But you ſuppoſe, becauſe it is ſayd in the coniecture you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, that they were collected and digeſted into the forme they are in, after the Councell was done, that therfore they were not written in any forme, no not at all in the Councell it ſelfe; to which purpoſe you ſay, that it was alwayes the vſe of Councells to write their owne decrees, <hi>and to ſigne them too,</hi> (as very pertinently you
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40746:24"/> adde) before they went away; intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hereby, that they did not ſo in this Councell; and your reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Pope Innocent did collect them into the forme they now are in, ſome while after the Councell was done. Surely you did not conſider what all impartiall men would conceiue of your ability, ſeeing you make ſuch an inference as this; ſo poore, that few in the world would haue made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues guilty of the like. And I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of all the world, whether the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Councell could not be written, <hi>and ſigned too,</hi> by, and in the Councell, and yet be brought into this forme, or method, wherein theynow are by Pope Innocent ſome while after? euery one that hath but common ſenſe will conclude againſt you. Yea his collecting and putting them into a forme ſome while after, is à proofe (cleane contrary to what you inferre, namely) that they were written ſome where, and in ſome forme or other before. For otherwiſe from whence should Pope Innocent
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40746:24"/> collect theſe decrees? out of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory? that is moſt improbable. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection imports not the inuenting or making them, but the gathering of them out of ſome Records or other; and out of the originall it is moſt likely (if he gathered them at all) that he tooke his collection, ſeeing he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the time and place of this Councell, and was preſent and preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent therein. Your argument then is no better than this, The Scriptures of the Prophets and Apoſtles were col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and brought into a forme writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and printed, againe and againe, after the firſt writers were dead and gone; therfore they were not at firſt written by themſelues or their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes.</p>
                  <p>You further labour to aſſoyle Pope Innocent from the guilt of forging theſe Decrees, (for you take it for graunted that they were forged, and Cochlaeus you are moſt conſtant to, for the man that forged them,) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Pope Innocent was not ſo weake aſcribe (you ſay) to make the Synode
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40746:25"/> quote it ſelfe; Wherein you might well haue ſpared your paynes, for <hi>Quis (quaeſo) vnquam vituperauit Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem?</hi> who, I pray, euer accuſed Pope Innocent hereof? you thinke Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus doth, becauſe he coniectures (as you ſay) that theſe Decrees were col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and brought into this forme by Pope Innocent, after the Councell was diſſolued; as if to collect decrees, and bring them into ſome or other forme after the diſſolution of the Councell, were all one as to forge them? A conceipt ſurely vnworthy of any iudicious man. Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the Pope (you ſay, and truly,) was not ſo weake a Scribe as to make the Synod quote it ſelfe, he knew well enough what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to it. Yet ſo vnhappy are you, that you cannot ſupport this truth, (which no body puts you to, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying) but by affirming a greater falshood, namely, that this Councell doth cite it ſelfe. But if you had beene ſo good a Scribe, as to haue knowne aſwell what belongeth to the making of obiections againſt a Councell, as
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40746:25"/> Pope Innocent did the ſtile of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, you would I thinke haue kept your owne counſell, and beene more ſilent in this matter. But you goe on, and ſay.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>Wee had beſt therfore belieue Platina, <hi>non eſt decretum ibi quicquam; non potuit ibi decerni quicquam. Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauit Innocentius ipſe Abbatis Ioa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim libellum, damnauit ipſe Alme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum.</hi> He ſayes, It was not the Councell of Lateran that made any decrees to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them; but that Pope Innocent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned them himfelſe. And wee may well conclude, <hi>That both theſe and other things, de quibus nihil decerni potuit in Concilio,</hi> were by the Pope ſet downe in his owne Decretalls; out of which he tooke thoſe Canons, whoeuer he was that compiled them into the forme of a Councell.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>You ſay, wee had beſt therfore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue Platina; which I graunt wee may doe, but not your ſenſe of his words, which I haue already refuted. But
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40746:26"/> what degree of truſt ſoeuer wee yeeld vnto Platina himſelfe, I am ſure wee had beſt giue none vnto you, in your citation of Platina, who haue wronged both him and vs, in all that you haue heere alleadged. All that he ſayes, is what you brought, and is anſwered in the beginning, <hi>nec decerni tamen quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apertè potuit;</hi> inſteed whereof you make him ſay, <hi>non eſt decretum ibi quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potuit ibi decerni quicqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in beſides the explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of the words, you leaue out the mayne word <hi>apertè,</hi> which changeth the whole ſenſe. Platina ſaith, <hi>nothing could be decreed openly,</hi> you alleadge him ſaying, <hi>there was not, nor could be any thing at all decreed,</hi> whereas the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing of nothing openly, doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that ſomething was decreed, though not openly; and for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Platina's words, I referre the reader to the firſt paragraph, where I shew, that theſe words of Platina were ſpoken with relation to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Holy warres, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the decrees of this Councell.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40746:26"/>
                  <p>And as heere you leaue out a word to the corrupting of the ſenſe, ſo in the following words which you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, (as if they were placed in Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina as they are in you, and were a further proofe of the ſame aſſertion, whereas they haue no connexion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſenſe, and are aboue a dozen lines aſunder,) you put in a word, which is the very hindge on which the ſenſe is turned, and turned contrary to the aſſured truth thereof; and that is the word, <hi>Ipſe, he himſelfe,</hi> as if the condemnation of Almericus and the booke of Ioachim had beene the Popes act without the Councell, that ſo you might proue the Councell fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified, wherein the ſayd acts are recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to haue paſſed. And then you adde as another ſaying of Platina, or as your conſtruction of the former words of Platina, <hi>He ſayes, it was not the Councell of Lateran that made any decrees to condemne them, but that Pope Innocent condemned them himſelfe.</hi> But Platina hath neither any ſuch formall words, nor are they the meaning of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40746:27"/> the words he hath; for his ſaying the Pope did condemne them, doth not neceſſarily imply that the Councell of Lateran did not condemne them, for it might be done by both, either ſeuerally or together, and this latter way it was done, as I haue already proued, and doe now againe by the teſtimony of<note n="a" place="margin">Beluac. l. <hi>30</hi> hiſt. cap. <hi>64.</hi>
                     </note> Beluacenſis, who ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Councell ſaith, that the Abbot Ioachim and Almericus were condemned therein. So that you are <hi>Ipſe, He himſelfe,</hi> that haue falſified Platina, layd vniuſt obiections againſt the Councell of Lateran, and <hi>(apertè) manifeſtly</hi> condemned your ſelfe of fowle play by the euidence of the fact,</p>
                  <p>For a cloſe to this ſection, you ſay, wee may well conclude, that both theſe and other things <hi>de quibus nihil decerni potuit in Concilio,</hi> were by the Pope ſet downe in his owne Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls; out of which he tooke theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, whoeuer he was that compiled them into the forme of a Councell. Your concluſion is like your premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40746:27"/> there is no truth in either of them both; you ſay, that both theſe and other things, (I ſuppoſe you meane all the Canons aſcribed to this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,) were ſet downe by the Pope in his owne Decretalls, that is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your meaning, inuented by the Pope, and put firſt into his Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls; for if they were firſt decreed in Councell, and afterwards put into the Decretalls, it is not for your purpoſe, but againſt you; and that it was ſo, I haue already ſufficiently proued; and doe yet againe by the title of theſe conſtitutions, as they are ſet downe in the Decretalls; which are not barely aſcribed to the Pope, as many others are; but to him in a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell; thus, <hi>Innocentius tertius in Concilio generali.</hi> Wee may therefore well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; that your concluſion built on your extreme corruption of Platina, hauing ſo rotten a foundation muſt needs fall to the ground.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly you ſay, that he tooke them out of the Popes owne Decretalls, whoeuer he was that compiled the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40746:28"/> Canons into the forme of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. But I haue proued before, that he tooke them out of the originall Records of the Councell; and if he had taken them out the Popes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretalls, it had bene well enough; thoſe Decretalls not being the Popes <hi>owne,</hi> ſingly, as you haue ſayd, but the Popes and Councells of Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran together, as I haue many wayes proued. So that of all that you haue hitherto ſayd, there is not one word but is either vntrue, or impertinent; and to vſe your owne words, <hi>de qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nihil decerni poteſt.</hi> Yet as if you had not ſayd enough of this nature, you goe on to make faults, in ſteed of finding them (as you ſuppoſe) in others.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>For the third Canon of this Councell (concerning the excommunication of temporall Princes, and the Popes power to free their ſubiects from all obedience to them, and to giue away their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes) is indeed one of the Extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gants;, cap. 13. de Haereticis, that is, Pope Innocents owne Decree, and not the Councells of Lateran, <hi>vbi nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerni
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40746:28"/> potuit.</hi> So in the 71. Canon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the recouery of the Holy Land from the Saracens (for which this Councell was chiefly called, and met together) the compiler hath made the words to run in a Popes ſtile, and not in the ſtile of a Councell, <hi>Ad liberan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam terram ſanctam de manibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piorum, ſacro Concilio approbante definimus, &amp;c.</hi> neither in the Councell was there any ſuch Decree made; as both Card. Bellarmine (againſt king Iames's Apologie,) and Eudaemon Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius <hi>(in his Parall. Torti &amp; Tortur.)</hi> doe confeſſe out of Platina. He therfore that made theſe two decrees, of abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſubiects from obedience to their Princes, and of recouering the land of promiſe from the Saracens, may well be thought to haue made that decree alſo of Tranſubſtantiation, which hath made ſuch a noyſe in the world, and for which this Councell is ſo often quoted vnder the name of <hi>Maximum omnium, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerale, &amp; celeberrimum Concilium.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The third Canon of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40746:29"/> concerning the excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of temporall Princes, you ſay, is one of the Extrauagants, <hi>cap. 13. de Haereticis,</hi> but you are very Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uagant in ſaying ſo; for there is no ſuch matter in the place by you cited, nor indeed any ſuch place as you haue here rashly ſet downe. All that is to be found is this; that in the fifth booke of the Extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gants, there is a Title <hi>de Haereticis,</hi> vnder which title are only three chapters, and in them not a word of this matter. And this for the truth of your quotation; I will now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſenſe of what you ſay, and the truth thereof. The third Canon (ſay you) is one of the Extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gants, that is, Pope Innocents owne Decree. By which it ſeemes, that it is the ſame thing with you, to be one of the Extrauagants, and to be Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts owne Decree; as if the Extrauaga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were Pope Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts owne decrees; whereas it is appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to whom they are aſcribed, that not one of them was made by Pope In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; ſo mightily are you miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40746:29"/> in this matter. This Decree then is not Pope Innocents owne, and not the Councells of Lateran, as you ſay, but Pope Innocents owne, and the Councells of Lateran; his, in and with the Councell of Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, as I haue proued. You alſo cite your ſelfe (for it is to be found in no authour elſe) againſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Lateran, ſaying, <hi>vbi nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerni potuit, where nothing could be decreed;</hi> againſt which I oppoſe (beſides all that I haue ſayd before) a man of much better authority, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Crantzius, who ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Crantz. Metrop. l. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. Innoc. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium maximum congregauit Latera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num; ibi multa conſtituta, quae hodie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in corpore iuris, there many things were decreed, which are at this day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the body of the law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreouer the ſenſe of this Canon you doe lamely, and with change of the tearmes ſet downe; for there is no mention of kings nor king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; and then the Popes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing of the <hi>vaſſalls of temporall Lords</hi> (for thoſe are the words of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40746:30"/> the Canon) from their fidelity to them, and expoſing their land to be occupied by Catholiques, expreſt to be but in the caſe of neglect to purge their land of hereſy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance therein after excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by the Bishops, and after a yeeres contempt of making ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and then there is added this reſeruation alſo, <hi>Saluo iure Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini principalis, &amp;c. ſauing the right of the principall Lord, ſo that he giue no obſtacle hereunto, nor oppoſe any impediment.</hi> Now this power of the Pope, whatſoeuer it be, is farre from that which your confuſed words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate, which to your weaker readers (I ſuppoſe) will ſound, as if the Pope had power to abſolue the ſubiects of any kings from their fidelity, and diſpoſe of their kingdomes when, to whom, and for what cauſe ſo euer they pleas'd; which is nothing ſo. Yet if this power of the Popes were ſo vaſt as you belieue it, or would haue others to belieue it, why should it trouble you? And why should you
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40746:30"/> be more tender of the intereſt of Princes than they themſelues, and all their courts about them, who either receiued this Canon imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly from the Councell, as I haue ſayd and proued, or elſe ſuffered it to be coſeningly thruſt vpon them, as you haue ſayd, but not proued.</p>
                  <p>And I wonder that you a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, should faſten vpon this decree of depoſing of Princes by the Pope, (to make the decrees of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell odious and incredible,) when as it is well knowne, that the Popes in ſixteene hundred yeeres, haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſo many, as Proteſtants in one hundred; for almoſt wherſoere the gangrene of that hereſy hath ſpread it ſelfe, they haue either actually depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and expelled their Princes, as in Swede, Denmarke, Scotland, Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, Geneua; or diuers times atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by violence to doe it, as in France often, in Bohemia, in Poland, and now it is feared in England. And if you ſay, that though theſe Puritane Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants haue both taught and done
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40746:31"/> theſe things, yet the true Proteſtant of the Church of England, he neuer taught ſuch doctrine, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not thinke ſuch a thought without horror; ſurely wee haue nothing but your bare and often broken word for our ſecurity. For what experience hath the king, or his few predeceſſors of your religion had, that in caſe they should haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued you of your deſires, as they denyed to graunt the deſires of the Puritanes, if they should haue turned you out of your Bishoppricks and Deaneries, taken from you the Church vſurped Liuings, ſet vp a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that would not haue endured wiuing preachers, what experience haue they had, that in theſe or the like caſes, your Proteſtants of the Church of England would not attempt their deſtruction, and if they were able, lay the axe on their necks, as your Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Gouuernour of your Church of England Queene Elizabeth and her inſtruments did, on the necke of the renowned Mary Queene of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Dowager of France.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:40746:31"/>
                  <p>Can you then thinke much that the Pope, a perſon of an other quality, and more diſ-intereſſed than the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of Princes, should haue ſome kinde of power, by all conuenient wayes to reduce and correct hereticall Princes? Eſpecially ſeeing the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, and Princes gaue their votes vnto this Decree, and were, for ſo much as concerned themſelues, the makers thereof. But you will not belieue that this decree was made in the Councell, but thinke that you haue proued the contrary. My aduice then is that you acquaint the Kings and Princes on this ſide the ſeas, with this ſtrange cheat that is put vpon them; it is like to be a matter of high acceptation to them, of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to their vnfaithfull ſeruants, that would not diſcouer that which you haue done, and of great prayſe and preferment to your ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>You further obiect againſt the Act of the expedition for the recouery of the Holy Land, (which you call the 71. Canon, but no body elſe doth ſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40746:32"/> that I know) becauſe it runnes, ſay you, in a Popes ſtile not in the ſtile of à Councell. By which I perceiue, that though you are one of the Court yet you are none of the Councell, for you are not skild in the ſtiles of Popes and Councells.</p>
                  <p>Otherwiſe you would haue knowne, that it is the manner in thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells where the Pope himſelfe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to decree things in his name, with this addition, <hi>ſacro approbante Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio,</hi> as in the Councell of Florence <hi>in literis vnionis,</hi> euen as Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England, are made in the kings name, <hi>with the aduice or conſent of the two houſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſay moreouer, that Card. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine and Eudaemon Cidonius doe confeſſe out of Platina, that there was no ſuch decree made. Your Eudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cidonius I cannot meet with heere, nor is it much materiall, for that answer which ſerues your quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bell: will ſerue him alſo, ſeeing (as you ſay) it is both their confeſſions out of Platina. For the finding of your citatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s out of Bell: you vſe vs very ill,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40746:32"/> giuing vs no direction, but a booke of perhaps twenty leaues in folio to finde out twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty words, which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee haue found, to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence our paynes, we finde your miſtake and falshood. For Bellarm. doth not ſpeake directly of the particular chapter of the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whether that were made in the Councell or no, but of the buiſineſſe of the Holy Warre in generall, <hi>de hoc articulo, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multa diſputata fuiſſent, nihil certi definiri potuit;</hi> and there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſure betwixt <hi>nihil certi,</hi> and <hi>nihil omnino,</hi> nothing certaine, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, as you would haue it. And I ſuppoſe this <hi>nihil certi</hi> is meant in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the further and more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular managing of the warre, from which they were hindred by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent warre in Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, and which is no denyall of the Decree of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, which conſiſts of a few ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall heads concerning the rayſing of contributions to this great worke from the clergy, (wherein the Pope himſelfe gaue a great example) of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments on thoſe that hindred it
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40746:33"/> and indulgence to them that aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it, with the like. All which though they were vndoubtedly decreed, yet it may be ſayd with Bell: out of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina, that after much diſputation there was nothing certaine defined, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the neerer and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar articles for the managing of the warre, being put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it by the preſent warre in Chriſtendome. Yea it might be ſayd <hi>nihil certi</hi> in regard of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree it ſelfe, not of the letter and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of it, but of the wars at home, yea rather the contrary was certaine, namely, that it was not executed. And if Platina (or Bellarmine out of him) had intended to exclude this Decree of the expedition (which is all that wee affirme to be done in that kinde) why did they expreſſe it with theſe reſeruations, of <hi>apertè</hi> and <hi>certi,</hi> and not ſay directly and without limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>nihil</hi> as you doe? which had beene more plaine, and agreeable to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity of thoſe writers. Therfore by theſe reſeruations they muſt needs intend ſome thing, which (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40746:33"/> is that which I haue expreſſed. Howſoeuer, certaine wee are, that this Decree was made in the Councell, by all that proofe whereby wee haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the whole Councell, of which this is a part; and particularly (becauſe you heere make a particular obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt it) by Matth. Paris, who inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mateth ſo much, by repeating<note n="a" place="margin">Matth. Paris hiſt. ma. p. <hi>189.</hi>
                     </note> the ſubſtance of this very Decree, in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many words as they are in the Councell, which are too long to ſet downe heere.</p>
                  <p>Your further ſay, that he that made theſe two decrees, of abſoluing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from obedience to their Princes, and of recouering the land of Promiſe from the Saracens, may well be thought to haue made the decree of Tranſubſtantiation alſo. And you ſay truth in that, but it will not helpe you; for Pope Innocent made them all, but, <hi>ſacro approbante Concilio,</hi> that is, the whole Councell, conſiſting of the Pope and the reſt of the Prelats, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed them Nor haue you reaſon ſo to boggle at the word Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40746:34"/> or at this Councell for the word; ſeeing the thing knew no begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſince our Sauiour, as our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique bookes doe ſufficiently proue; and euen the word it ſelfe was in vſe before this Councell, as appeareth by <hi>Roger Houenden in Henrico 2.</hi> where he hath theſe words.<note n="b" place="margin">Annal. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.576.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Confeſsi ſunt etiam, quod Sacerdos noſter, bonus ſiue malus, iustus vel iniuſtus, corpus &amp; ſanguinem Chriſti poſset conficere, &amp; perminiſterium huiuſmodi Sacerdotis, &amp; virtutem diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum verborum, quae à Domino prolata ſunt, panis &amp; vinum in corpus &amp; ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Chriſti verè tranſubſtantiantur.</hi> Alſo by Bleſenſis, who was king Henry the ſecond his Chaplayne, who ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Bleſenſ. p. <hi>140.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Et vt gratia exempli, in vno Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentorum videas abyſſum profundiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, &amp; humano ſenſui imperceptibilem, pane &amp; vino tranſubſtantiatis virtute verborum caeleſtium in corpus &amp; ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Chriſti &amp;c.</hi> Both theſe wrote in the dayes of Henry the ſecond, and the Councell of Lat. was held in the dayes of king Iohn, who raigned the ſecond after him. And in both theſe good
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40746:34"/> English authors, doe wee finde the word <hi>tranſubſtantiated,</hi> applyed to the bread &amp; wine cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt; nor doe wee finde in any ſtory, that theſe men were que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned for the vſe of theſe words, as if they did import any thing more in their ſenſe, than that which was the generall beliefe of that and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going ages. It is not therfore the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of tranſubſtantiation made in this Councell afterwards, which hath made ſuch a noyſe in the world, as you ſay it hath, but the heretiques and Schiſmatiques that haue oppoſed it.</p>
                  <p>Nor was this Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell for this decrees ſake called <hi>Maximu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, generale, &amp; celeberrimum,</hi> but becauſe it was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by the Pope fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all parts of the Chriſtian world, and there met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the greateſt and moſt renowned aſſembly both of Clergy and Laity, that euer was in the world: which therfore it ill becomes you to deride. In fine, the three particular decrees you heere oppoſe, but haue proued
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40746:35"/> nothing againſt them, are firſt inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Decretalls, which was done by Pope Gregory IX. not many yeeres after the Councell was held; who therein vſed the ſeruice of one of the beſt men of the world, as I haue proued before. Secondly, they are put into the number of the Canons of this Councell by Crab: who (as I haue alſo proued) tooke them out of the Originall Records. Thirdly, they are alſo reckoned amongſt the reſt of the Canons, by all others that haue made edition of this Councell, as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Binius, and whoſoeuer elſe. Laſtly, they are receiued and allowed by the Catholique Church, the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt teſtimony of all others; and doe you thinke to ouerthrow them? Who is ſufficient for this? he therfore that attempts it, deſerues the name of <hi>hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticorum maximus omnium, generalis &amp; celeberrimus.</hi> In the next place, you inuade vs with an Arithmeticall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument; but when I haue reckoned with you, it will appeare that you are not a man of good account; for thus you caſt it;</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:40746:35"/>
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>But as it should ſeeme, he that firſt compoſed it, and ſtiled it ſo, or afterwards ſet it forth, and entituled it a Generall Councell, had not his leſſon perfect. For betweene the ſeuenth and the eighth Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell, I trow there cannot another Generall Councell interueene, as this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is made to doe, if it were ſo Great and ſo Generall, as they ſay it is. They count the ſecond of Nice for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Generall, which was held in the yeare 787. and the Councell of Florence (held in the yeare 1449.) for the eighth Generall, as is there, in the laſt ſeſsion of it, expreſsly ſet downe; <hi>Finis octaui Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii Generalis factus eſt 21. Iulii &amp;c.</hi> So that vnleſſe they will make two eight generall Councells, this of Lateran could be none.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>You paſſe from the matter of this Councell, to diſproue the title therof; and ſay, he that entituled it a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell had not his leſſon perfect, and that becauſe (as you ſay) they count the ſecond of Nice for the ſeuenth generall Councell, and the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40746:36"/> Councell of Florence for the eighth, &amp; betweene the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th and the eighth there cannot another interueene, as this is made to doe, if it were ſo great and ſo generall, as they ſay it is. Truly if he that published this Councell, had had his leſſon no perfecter than he that made theſe obiections, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be whipt for a trewant, for neuer were there ſuch idle obiections made. I pray who are theſe, <hi>they,</hi> that account the Councell of Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the eighth generall Councell? your reader cannot but thinke you meane vs Roman Catholiques, againſt whom you heere diſpute, and whom you would make to appeare ſo ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they cannot tell eight. But it is not the Roman account, <hi>I trow,</hi> that you heere follow, but the ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Grecian, who yet will giue you no more thankes for it, nor no more admitt you a member of their Church, than will the Catholiques. You muſt know then, if you did not before, that the eighth generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell was celebrated in Conſtantinople
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40746:36"/> againſt Photius, who made a ſchiſme betweene the Latin and Greeke Church, they of the ſchiſme reiected this eighth, and many other generall Councells, which were celebrated in the weſt; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt which this fourth of Lateran (you ſo ſtrongly and weakly fight againſt) was one; vntill the Grecians meeting againe with the Latins in the Councell of Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the Grecians called that the eighth generall Councell; which yet ſoone after they reiected, and ſo at this day allow but ſeuen. But if men may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and reiect Councells at their pleaſure, then you may with the Lutherans allow but ſix; with the Eutychians which are yet in Aſia, but the firſt three; with the Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians which are yet in the Eaſt, but the firſt two; with the Arrians and Trinitarians which are in Hungary and Poland, none at all. And this you and yours may doe with as good reaſon, as they doe reiect and reuile this of Lateran, and aboue all, the ſacred Oecumenicall Councell of Trent.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:40746:37"/>
                  <p>And that you may againe fall into the fault, of which you falsely accuſe others; you are out in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the yeeres of the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Councell of Florence; but this I doe not mention as a matter of moment, it being brought in but on the by. But I cannot omitt a weighty paſſage that you haue a little before, where you ſay, that betweene the ſeuenth and the eighth generall Councell you trow, there cannot come another, if it were ſo great and ſo generall, as this is ſayd to be. Wherby you intimate, that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this Councell was the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that it could not come betweene the ſeuenth and the eighth, and by conſequence, that if it had beene a little one, it might haue come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene; which is a very new and pretty fancy. A little generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell it ſeemes might haue crowded in betweene the ſeuenth and the eighth as an <hi>appendix</hi> to the former, or otherwiſe haue found place and vnion with it vnder the ſame name and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40746:37"/> number of the ſeuenth, but this being ſo great and ſo generall, could not poſſibly finde a roome betwixt them, but that it muſt make two eights, as you ſay, rather than an eighth and a ninth, which ninth (if it had beene ſo, in this caſe) might yet haue beene called the eighth in ſome other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, as I haue shewed. But I had thought that Councells in regard of number being of <hi>diſcrete quantity,</hi> did not require any place by reaſon of their greatneſſe, (as if they were in this regard, of <hi>continued quantity</hi> alſo,) more than if they had beene little: the abſtract number of eight, (I trow) can no more come in, betweene ſeuen and eight, in a ſmall ſubiect tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a great; and therfore the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this Councell was no more hinderance to its coming in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſeuenth and the eighth, without cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging the name and order of the number, than if it had beene neuer ſo little.</p>
                  <p>You tell vs alſo, that in the laſt ſeſſion of the Councell of Florence
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40746:38"/> it is expreſſely ſet downe, <hi>Finis octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui Concilij generalis, &amp;c.</hi> yet the words more expreſſely than you haue ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe are, <hi>Finis generalis octauae Synodi,</hi> which though not different in ſubſtance, yet the difference of the words <hi>Concilium</hi> and <hi>Synodus</hi> if you had vnderſtood the reaſon thereof, had beene enough to preuent your obiection. For it appeares hy an epiſtle of Bartholomaeus Abramus to the Archbishop of Rauenna, ſet downe by Crab at the beginning of this Councell, and by Binius at the end, that the Latin Originall of this Councell was loſt, and that this that is now extant, was tranſlated by the ſayd Abramus out of the Greeke, for which reaſon he vſeth the word <hi>Synodus</hi> according to the Greeke, &amp; not <hi>Concilium;</hi> and it is called <hi>octaua</hi> becauſe it was ſo in the greeke which hee tranſlated; and the Greekes ſet it downe ſo, becauſe (as I ſayd before) they accounted no Councells gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but where they themſelues were preſent and which they did receiue,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40746:38"/> of which this was indeed the eighth. But this account is (for very good reaſons) reiected by<note n="a" place="margin">Praefat. huic Synod.</note> Surius and<note n="b" place="margin">Notis in Concil. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</note> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, and by all Catholiques. And Crab though hee haue no <hi>caueat</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this place, yet that you may ſee he ſpake according to the letter of the greeke coppy, and not his owne minde, he calleth all the Councells betwixt the 2. of Nice, and Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, Generall Councells; all that the Church accounteth ſo; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of this Councell of Lateran he ſayth, <hi>Inſtituta generalis Concilij Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranenſis tempore Innocentij Papae tertij.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the end of this ſection you make this notable concluſion; <hi>So that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they will make two eight generall Councells, this of Lateran could be none;</hi> which out of your diſcourſe may as iuſtly be inferred thus, ſo that vnleſſe they will make two, or nine eight generall Councells, that of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople the fourth, the fower of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran, the two of Lions, that of Vienne, that of Piſa, that of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or ſome one of theſe could be
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40746:39"/> none. Could be none, is a falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, could not be the eighth, is true; nor is that of Florence or La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran numbred for the eighth by any Catholiques at this day, but this is reckoned the twelfth, that moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the ſixteenth. But that the number of eight, which you ſo hunt heere, may come in (becauſe <hi>nos nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meri ſumus</hi>) he that firſt made this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection (which I belieue was not you) shall by my conſent be reckoned <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientum octauus, the eighth wiſe man,</hi> which he shall be without a riuall, there shall not be two of them; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if he that next aſpires to it be a great one, for then <hi>(I trow)</hi> he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>interucene</hi> in the order of number, betweene the eighth and the ninth, as you haue taught vs for our learning.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>Beſides, if it were a generall Councell, how came it to paſſe, that the Canons of it were neuer generally receiued? as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs in the Church and kingdome of England they were not, and as without doubt they would haue beene, had the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40746:39"/> Councell in thoſe dayes beene accounted generall, and the Decrees of it vnder that ſtile and title ſent abroad into the world. But with vs in England euer ſince that time, and contrary to the 46. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Canon of it, ſubſidies haue beene payd to the king, <hi>inconſulto Pontifice;</hi> and againſt the 41. Canon, with vs <hi>Currit praeſcriptio,</hi> though oftentimes <hi>ex bona fide ortum non habeat;</hi> and yet againe contrary to the third Canon there, with vs, <hi>Clericorum bona qui de haereſi conuicti ſunt,</hi> they goe not to the vſe of the Church, but are alwayes brought into the kings Exchequer.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>The generality of this Councell you further goe about to diſproue, becauſe the Canons thereof were not (as you ſay) generally receiued; and this you proue, becauſe they were not receiued in England; but that they were not receiued in England you doe not proue, but by three inſtances, which you doe not proue; and if you had, they had proued nothing. For it is not properly the generall receiuing
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40746:40"/> that makes a Councell to be generall, but the generall calling thereof from all parts of the Chriſtian world, and ſuch was this. Otherwiſe no Councell could be ſtiled generall in the calling of it, or while it was ſitting, or when it was concluded, vntill it did appeare that all the world had receiued it, which is a condition that neuer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to any Councell, becauſe ſome or other heretiques (againſt whom all generall Councells haue beene commonly called) or perhaps all, did refuſe to receiue it. So that by this your character of a generall Councell, you haue plainly casheired all the generall Councells that euer were, for euen the firſt fower, which you ſeeme to magnifie, and grant them the title of Generall, were the Canons of them generally receiued? It is manifeſt that they were not, but were reiected by all thoſe ſorts of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques who were the occaſion of their calling.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer, your reaſon to proue that the canons of this Councell of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40746:40"/> Lateran were not generally receiued to wit, becauſe they were not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in England; if it were true, yet it is inconſequent, and your deceipt or miſtake lyeth in the indiſtinction of the word <hi>Canons,</hi> whereof ſome be of faith, ſome of manners and diſcipline. Now that a Councell be accounted to be generally receiued, it is not required that the Canons of diſcipline and practiſe be receiued in all kingdomes, but it is ſufficient that the Canons concerning mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith be generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, to ſtile the reception gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the Councell generall, for ſo much as the generality of recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can contribute to the title of its being generall. As for example, the kingdome of France doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the decrees of the Councell of Trent concerning gouernment, but of faith it doth, as doe all other Catholique Countries, for which reaſon, euen this kingdome which denies to receiue the Councell of Trent in matters of gouernment,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40746:41"/> doth notwithſtanding acknowledge it generall. By which it appeares, that you are not ſo well verſed in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councells and their reception, as to know diſtinctly the meaning of the words according to their Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique vſe. Now there is no doubt that the kingdome of England did receiue this Councell for the matters of faith, otherwiſe it would haue beene noted hereticall as now it is, and for its not receiuing the Canons of diſcipline and gouernment, you proue not but by your owne bare word, which I may moſt iuſtly deny; yet I haue other proofes againſt you.</p>
                  <p>But firſt I will take notice of your miſtake (if not vnfaithfullneſſe) in your deſcription of the 46. <hi>pretended</hi> Canon (as you call it) contrary to which, you ſay, ſubſidies haue beene payd to the king, <hi>inconſulto Pontifice;</hi> as if that Canon had ſayd, that no ſubſidies at all should be payd to the king but by the aduice of the Pope, whereas the Canon ſpeakes only of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40746:41"/> the ſubſidies of the Clergy, as requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Popes aduice. As for the practiſe of England contrary to theſe three Canons you mention, if it be true (which I doe not belieue, becauſe I haue heard good lawyers in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſay the contrary in one, which concernes preſcription) yet it doth not proue that theſe Canons were not receiued; for theſe croſſings of the Canons may happen, either through indulgence of the Pope granted to the kings, or the kings vſurpation contrary to the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s receiued; or in your inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of preſcription, through the headſtrong impiety of the people, who will not obſerue the good lawes they receiue, being contrary to their euill cuſtomes . If England had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued all the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s they haue heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore receiued, when they were as wiſe, as learned, as pious, as iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious (at the leaſt) as now they are, you and I (I belieue) should not haue beene at this bay, that now we are. Now contrary to your proofeleſſe aſſertion, I proue that the Canons of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40746:42"/> this Councell were receiued in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as well thoſe of manners as of faith; firſt by the teſtimony of Linwood, and the municipall lawes of the land, as they are affirmed by <hi>Franciſcus à ſancta Clara,</hi> in his article of tranſubſtantiation.</p>
                  <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly by the Councell of Oxford before cited, held by the then Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, but ſeuen yeeres after this of Lateran, (which was the very firſt Councell in the world, that was held after this) where it is ſayd,<note n="a" place="margin">Binij tom. <hi>7.</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>833.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>That all things may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded wich a good end, wee enioyne that the Lateran Councell celebrated vnder Pope Innocent of holy memory, in the paying of tithes, and in the other chapters be obſerued.</hi> By which it appeares, how much you are deceiued, in ſaying that in England the Canons of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell were not receiued: as you alſo are in ſaying.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>Lastly, I belieue no good ſtory can be shewed to confirme the pretended title of this Councell, that the Patriarch of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40746:42"/> and Conſtantinople were preſent at it, and 70. Metropolitans beſides; though that will not make it generall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for want of the two other Patriarchs of Antioche and Alexandria, who are not mentioned to haue beene among them. Howſoeuer, <hi>nihil ibi actum quod qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem conſtet;</hi> and ſo was it neither any Generall Councell, nor ſo much as any Councell at all.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>What you belieue imports not, for I know you belieue many hereſies and errors, amongſt which errors this is one, That no good ſtory can be shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Patriarchs of Ieruſalem and Conſtantinople were preſent at this Councell &amp;c. One is ſayd to be preſent either in perſon or by deputy; that thoſe two Patriarchs which you firſt mention, were there in perſon, is affirmed by Platina, Paris, and Vrſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pergenſis; and that the other two were there by their deputies, with aboue 70. Metropolitanes, beſides a very great number of Archbishops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Abbots, and Priors, ſome in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40746:43"/> perſon, and ſome by Proxy; and with theſe the Legats and deputies of the two Emperours, of all (or almoſt all) the Kings, Princes, citties and other places of the Chriſtian world, is recorded by Paris, and Vrſpergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis. And I ſuppoſe you will not deny any of them to be good hiſtorians, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially Paris and Platina, whom you called in, in the beginning of this your worke, as witneſſes (as you thought) againſt the Canons of this Councell. <note n="a" place="margin">Matth. Paris. hiſt. mai. p. <hi>188.</hi> l. e.</note> Paris and Vrſperge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis ſpeake almoſt in the ſame words;<note n="b" place="margin">Vrsper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſ. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. p. <hi>320.</hi>
                     </note> thus: <hi>Anno ab In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnatione Verbi</hi> 1215. <hi>celebrataeſt ſancta vniuerſalis Synodus Romae, in Eccleſia Saluatoris, quae Conſtantiniana vocatur, menſe Nouembri, praeſidente Domino In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentio Papa tertio, Pontificatus eius anno</hi> 18. <hi>in quo fuerunt Epiſcopi</hi> 412. <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quos extiterunt de praecipuis Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis duo, videlicet, Conſtant: &amp; Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol: Antiochenus autem graui languore detentus, venire non potuit, ſed miſit pro ſe Vicarium, Anthedarenſem Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum: Alexandrinus vero ſub Saraceno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum dominio conſtitutus, fecit quod po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40746:43"/> mittens pro ſe Diaconum ſuum Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum; Primates autem &amp; Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam</hi> 71. <hi>caeterùm Abbates &amp; Priores vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra octingentos; Archiepiſcoporum vero &amp; Epiſcoporum, Abbatum, &amp; Priorum, &amp; Capitulorum abſentium Procuratorum non fuit certus numerus comprehenſus. Legatorum vero Regis Siciliae in Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Imperatorem electi, Imperatoris Constantinopolitani, Regis Franciae, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Angliae, Regis Vngariae, Regis Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolymitani, Regis Cypri, Regis Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniae, necnon &amp; aliorum Principum, &amp; Magnatum ciuitatum, aliorumque loco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fuit multitudo.</hi> Heere is your erroneous beliefe plainly and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply confuted. I wonder what hiſtories you haue read concerning this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, that theſe should eſcape you; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially <hi>Paris</hi> the Popes deare friend, and <hi>Platina the Popes owne Secretary.</hi> I haue therfore reaſon to belieue that you tooke vp theſe obiections vpon truſt, and of men that were not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, who haue greatly deceiued you. And therfore the title of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell which you againe ſo ſcornefully
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40746:44"/> and boldly call <hi>pretended,</hi> shall be really accounted Generall, by the beſt and nobleſt part of the world, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, when all other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Churches, Councells, and their Canons, their Bishops, Deanes, and Chapters shall haue no being, nor memory but of dishonour.</p>
                  <p>You further ſay, (according to your manner, without proofe,) that this Councell vas not Generall, for want of the perſonall preſence of two of the Patriarchs; wherein you are much miſtaken: for otherwiſe the firſt fower commonly ſtiled Generall, and for ſuch acknowledged by very many Proteſtants, cannot be truly ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Chiefe Patriarch, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome, was not preſent in any of them, but by his Legats. Vnleſſe you will ſay, that though two may not be abſent, yet one may, eſpecially when that one is the Pope, a man who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you (I know) can very well ſpare, not only out of the Councell, but out of the world. And yet I wonder that you that haue had the fortune to be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40746:44"/> the pretended Deane of S. Peters Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough and the pretended Maſter of S. Peters houſe, should yet be ſuch an enemy to S. Peters chayre. But if you deſire to know what makes a Councell generall, and what are the inſufficiencies thereof, which you ought to haue expreſſed and proued, before you had shot your haſty bolt of condemnation againſt this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, reade Turrecremata, and Canus vpon this ſubiect.</p>
                  <p>You at laſt conclude thus, How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, <hi>nihil ibi actum quod quidem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtet,</hi> and ſo was it neither any generall Councell, nor ſo much as any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at all. Wherein firſt your propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is falſe and hath no authority (that I know of) but the worſt in the world, your owne. Yet you ſet it downe in Latin, as if they were the words of ſome author, but neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the place, nor ſo much as his name, and therfore I take it for yours, and reiect it. Secondly if it were true that nothing was done there, yet your inference from thence is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40746:45"/> to wit, that therfore it was neither any generall Councell, nor ſo much as any Councell at all; concerning the nullities of a Councell, or of the generality therof, I need ſay no more than I haue done, ſeeing it reſts on you to proue, that doing nothing is one. And for your affirmation that nothing was done, I haue fully diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it through this whole diſcourſe. I will therfore only adde the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Matth. Paris, who though he were no friend to this Pope, as I haue shewed before, yet ſpeaking of this Councell in the place aboue cited, ſaith thus: <hi>His omnibus congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatis in ſuo loco praefato, &amp; iuxta mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Conciliorum Generalium in ſuis or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinibus ſingulis collocatis, facto prius ab ipſo Papa exhortationis ſermone, recitata ſunt in pleno Concilio capitula 60.</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is a miſtake in the figure, it should be 70.) <hi>quae aliis placabilia, aliis vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur oneroſa. Tandem de negotio Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixi &amp; ſubiectione terrae ſanctae verbum praedicationis exorſus, ſubiunxit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, Ad haec ne quid in negotio Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40746:45"/> Chriſti de contingentibus omitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, volumus &amp; mandamus, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo repeats at large the ſubſtance of the Decree of the Expedition for the recouery of the Holy land. So that it is manifeſt by this, and that which hath beene ſayd before, that there were many things done in this Councell, yea all that are affirmed to bee. And it is called a Councell, and a generall Councell, by <hi>Vrſpergenſis, Paris, Platina, Grantzius, Nauclerus, Beluace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis,</hi> and all that I can finde that haue any way written therof, except your vncontrowlable ſelfe. Beſides it hath the allowance of the Holy Catholique Church, the awfull ſpouſe of Chriſt, more true, more wiſe, more vigilant, and infinitly more reuerend then all the ſects &amp; Synagogues of Schiſmatiques, &amp; Heretiques; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt her, whom they ought to belieue and reuerence aboue all things on the earth, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they are propounded peremptorily, as theſe are, are fitter to be reiected than to be anſwered.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40746:46"/> I conclude with the words of Surius: <hi>
                        <hi rend="sup">a</hi> Nemo ſanae mentis ambigere poteſt, hanc quae ſequitur Synodum Lateranenſem cum primis inſignem &amp; vere oecumenicam fuiſſe, quippe in qua de negotiis religionis ſumma Latinae &amp; Graecae Eccleſiae concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia tractatum eſt, cuique interfuere Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarcha Conſtantinopolitanus, &amp; Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolymitanus, &amp; Archiepiſcopi tum La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni tum Graeci 70. Epiſcopi 412. Abbates &amp; Priores plus 800. ſimul omnes Praelati 1215. aut eo plures. Nec defuere Legati Graeci &amp; Romani Imperatoris, Regum Hieruſalem, Galliae, Hiſpaniae, Angliae, &amp; aliorum. Quod ſi verò ea cuiquam prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea minus ponderis habere videatur, quod recentior ſit, ille certè Chriſtum mendacem facere velle videtur, qui per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennem praeſentiam ſuam promiſit Eccleſiae ſuae, &amp; Spiritum ſanctum ſuum, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum veritatis, qui cum illa maneat in aeternum. Manet ſua ſemper Catholicae Eccleſiae authoritas, quam quiſquis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnere auſus eſt, non ille efficit vt ea minor ſit, ſed ſe dignum reddit, qui eius pondere penitus opprimatur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No man well in his wits can doubt,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40746:46"/> that this Councell of Lateran was very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and truly generall, becauſe therein were handled the matters of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with very great agreement of the Greeke and Latine Churches, &amp; wherin were preſent the Patriarch of Conſtantinople, and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and 70. Archbishops Greeke and Latin, Bishops 412. Abbots and Priors aboue 800. all the Prelats together were one thouſand two hundred and fifteene, or more. Neither were there abſent the Ambaſſadours of the Greeke and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperours, of the kings of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, France, Spayne, England, and others. But if this Councell ſeeme to any to haue leſſe weight, becauſe it is later, hee truly ſeemes to be willing to make Chriſt a lyar, who hath promiſed his perpetuall preſence to his Church, and his Holy Spirit, the Spirit of truth, which remayneth with her for euer? The autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Catholique Church doth alwayes abide here, which who ſoeuer preſumes to deſpiſe, he doth not leſſen her, but renders himſelfe worthy to be cruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to pieces with her weight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now inſteed of your prouing
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40746:47"/> the Catholique writers lyars, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and the Catholique Church credulous, negligent, and ignorant (which you endeauoured) you haue proued your ſelfe, vnwiſe, vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and audacious; and I belieue will looſe all credit and reputation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, or capacity, in the iudgement of all prudent men, of what religion ſoeuer they be, that shall reade theſe your vnworthy workes. But ſuppoſe the thing it ſelfe were true, that you haue laboured for (abſtracting the authority to the contrary) to wit, that there had beene no Canons made in this Councell, yea ſuppoſe there had neuer beene any ſuch thing as this Councell, what is it to your purpoſe? What article of our Catholique Faith is therby cancelled? how is your inuiſible Church of England, or your Chappell in France (where God hath his Church) defended? Not at all, by ought that you haue ſayd. No nor by your Mimique acting of the prieſt in hearing of confeſſions, (which wee perhaps shall heare too, at the third
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40746:47"/> or fourth hand, for as you haue no character of prieſthood for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Confeſſions, ſo neither haue you any ſeale vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your lippes) wherby though like the <hi>aſinus apud Cumanos</hi> in the lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s skin, you bray &amp; keepe ſome in awe, yet it may be they will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to diſcouer you, and make your vayne aſpiring the obiect of their contempt and laughter, as it is of ours, and euen of all your fellow reformadoes. Your owne concluſion therfore which you diſcharge againſt us, recoyles vpon your ſelfe, <hi>nihil ibi actum, quod quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſtet;</hi> in all that you haue done, it is certaine that you haue done nothing. And your obiections and diſcourſe haue in them neither any generall counſell, nor (except the Counſell of the vngodly) ſo much as any counſell at all.</p>
                  <p>And now let mee tell you, that it were much more for your credit, to forbeare ſuch bold brauing of the whole Catholique Church, eſpecially in a Catholique Country, and in the Court of a Catholique Queene, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40746:48"/> that with ſuch feeble and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>schollerly arguments; of which, (were not your iudgment ecclipſed by partiality, and your paſſion ſwelld by oppoſition, and your ouerweening conceipt of your ſelfe the producer of extraordinary confidence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence in you) you could not render your ſelfe guilty. Alſo your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous and offenſiue language, euen to the Maſters of thoſe ſchooles wherein you are not worthy to be a diſciple, is ſufficiently obſerued; though couered with that patience which you haue not deſerued; Otherwiſe, your weakeneſſe, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or both, would ere this haue beene characterd on your brow, had not the hands of our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Prieſts beene bound vp with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and charity, and reſpect to thoſe, who ſee, ſuffer, but (I belieue approue not your boyſterous beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. And in this buiſineſſe of writing, your shame is layd open with the bookes you cite, wherein your quotations are not ſooner examined,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40746:48"/> than your corruptions are diſcouered. If therfore you haue not grace e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to become a vertuous Roman Catholique, of which you made shew (as there is good proofe) when you came firſt into theſe parts, yet learne at leaſt to be rationall in your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, honeſt in your allegations, and ciuill in your language, both to particular reuerend and learned men, and eſpecially towards the whole Catholique Church. And then if you haue a diſpoſition to ſay or write any more, you shall be anſwered with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity, and equall ciuility.</p>
                  <p>And whereas one Mr Crowder hath reported, that I haue renounced the booke I lately ſet forth, and will not ſtand to it; and that Doctor Holden who approued it for Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, hath alſo refuſed to iuſtify it; or words to this purpoſe; and giueth this for his reaſon, why hee doth not publish the anſwer which he and his Coadiutors (as it is ſayd) haue framed thereunto: which is indeed but a retreate for their inability to anſwer
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40746:49"/> it; I ſay, it is falſe in him whoſoeuer ſaith it, and malicious in him that inuented it. And I further profeſſe to him and to the world, that (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſlanders to the contrary) I doe auow the ſayd booke for mine, and for Catholique, and ſo doth Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Holden. And if he, or any, or all his fellow Miniſters, will publish any thing that they will call an anſwer thervnto, they shall not looſe their labour, they shall haue a reply; wherein I make no queſtion their weakneſſe shall be made to appeare, as herein appeareth the weakneſſe of D. Coſens.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:40746:49"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>IF D. Coſens, or any one on his behalfe, shall ſay that I haue not heere ſet downe truly what he wrote; whoſoeuer deſires to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied therein, may if he pleaſe ſee the originall vnder his owne hand, which is in my keeping. And although his name be not ſet to it, yet euery one that knowes his hand, will grant he wrote it, and the Counteſſe of Denbigh by whoſe order I receiued it, ſayd that it was deliuered to her by Doctor Coſens. Which paper, and others of his alſo (he inwardly shrinking at his owne guilt) hath mightily laboured to recall into his owne hands, that ſoe there might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne no handwriting of his owne againſt him; but it was not fit that one of his temper should finde ſo much fauour, but that they should remayne vpon the perpetuall regiſtry of time, by being committed to the preſſe; ſeeing he hath deſerued to haue part of the diuine handwriting againſt
<pb facs="tcp:40746:50"/> him, that was againſt the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Baltazar; THEKEL, <hi>Thou art weighed in a ballance, and art found too light.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:40746:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 15. in the margent oner againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> line, put, <hi>pag.</hi> 877. <hi>C.</hi> p. 16. This quotation in the margent [vol. 2. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>15.] place it ſix lines higher. p. 39. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 24. after <hi>ſee it,</hi> adde, <hi>or ſeeing it.</hi> p. 40. l, 19. for <hi>yea.</hi> read, <hi>yet.</hi> p. 52. l. 12. for <hi>explication,</hi> read, <hi>duplication.</hi> p. 60. l. 3. before <hi>exprest,</hi> read, <hi>is</hi> p. 64. l. 14. after <hi>vnionis,</hi> adde, <hi>&amp; in diuers other Councells.</hi> p. 66. l. 13. after <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it,</hi> adde, but of the execution, which was not certaine, nor likely; and for <hi>but</hi> read <hi>becauſe.</hi> p. 68. l. 10 after iniuſtus draw a little line. p. 91 l. 10. after <hi>bee</hi> adde, <hi>done.</hi> p. 93. l. 23. for <hi>here,</hi> read <hi>hers.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
